A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program-Related Files, 1975-2019; 6; 32.9 Cubic Feet 94 containers
  - Journalism, 1975-2019; 7; 7.98 Cubic Feet 20 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter boxes
    - Survey and Studies, 1995-2010; 7.8
      - Killing The News: Stories Go Untold as Latin American Journalists Die, 2010 October 29 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4829
        Reporter's analysis by Tyler Bridges. This is one in a series of independently reported articles reviewing KF's own grant making.
    - Technology Innovation, 2014-2016; 7.9
      - Email News Alerts, 2014 October 28-2015 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 5476
        Email alerts re: a Knight Foundation partnership with The Paley Center for Media on their The Next Big Thing in Open Government series that will focus on the use of media and technology to accelerate open government in the digital age and Knight Prototype Fund deadline; an announcement of the winners of the Knight News Challenge on Libraries and the Knight News Challenge on Elections.
      - Conferences, 2015 January 28-July 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 5739
        Conferences coordinated by Media Innovation department in 2015: American Library Association Midwinter Conference (agenda); 2015 Knight Chair Meeting (agenda, participants); American Library Association Annual Meeting (memo, agenda, participants); Knight News Challenge Conference (memos, agenda); Prototype Demo Day (agenda).
      - Media Innovation Gathering, 2016 June 22-26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5737
        Program, participant list, and session write-ups for the Media Innovation Gathering conference in Orlando, FL. Also included is the program for the adjunct conference of the American Libraries Association Annual Conference. KF sponsored several panel discussions at that conference.
  - Learning and Assessment, 2010-2015; 8; 0.19 Cubic Feet 1 half-letter box
    - Evaluation of NPR Knight Training Program Proposal, 2010 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4814
      Proposed scope of work and budget for TCC group consultants to conduct an evaluation of the NPR Knight Training Program.
    - Strategy and Assessment Planning Meeting, 2013 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 5358
      Background information for the meeting includes 2014 budget, Teach for America report, Foundation Center report, Talent/Young Professionals Survey, Giving Day, New Americans Campaign, Trustee strategy session, and Civic Tech.
    - Q3 and Q4 Strategic Reviews, 2014 June 26-October 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5374
      Specific grants and initiatives were discussed at a strategic review meeting, in preparation for the September and December board meetings. Includes memos, participant feedback, and list of follow up items.
    - Quarterly Strategic Reviews, 2015 January 8-October 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5485
      Memos re: change in format for the 2015 strategic review meetings; agenda for the Q2 meeting; topics for the Q3 meeting include: Where is the Web going?, Knight Enterprise Fund, Voting, and Productizing Learning. Also included is a copy of "Internet Trends" by Mary Meeker. Topics to be discussed at the Q4 meeting include Funding Innovation, Building a Collaborative Mobile Learning Group, Developing a Common Language around Networks, and Meshing Intuition with Data. All KF staff were invited to attend the meeting.
    - Giving Days Webinars, 2015 July 22-September 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5568
      Information on a series of webinars sponsored by KF to provide community foundations with tools for greater Giving Days success. Featured KF staffer Anna Dilernia.
  - Learning and Impact, 2019; 9; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - Research, 2019; 9.1
      - RFP Research on the Future of an Informed Society, Guidance and Materials, 2019 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5988
        RFP Research on the Future of an Informed Society. Confidential. Reviewers book for second round submissions to the request for proposal launched in October 2018. Reviewers received the books in January 2019 and gathered in Miami to discuss in February 2019.
      - RFP Research on the Future of an Informed Society, Budget Outlines, 2019 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 5989
        RFP Research on the Future of an Informed Society, Budget Outlines. Materials provided to second round reviewers of the request for proposal.
  - National Programs and New Initiatives, 2007-2012; 10; 3.42 Cubic Feet 9 letter document boxes
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community, Narrative, 2008 July (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Knight File Number - 4742
      The goal of the Knight Foundation-Gallup Soul of the Community project was to measure citizens' engagement in each of the 26 KF communities in which they live. These reports add to the ongoing community narrative by showing how the citizens of the community feel about the place they live, what it has to offer them, and what they offer back to it. The data from this project are intended to be used to track the engagement of the community over time and to identify key strengths and opportunities for the communities. There is a narrative report for each community. 2 folders.
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community, 2008 July (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
      Knight File Number - 4743
      The goal of the Knight Foundation-Gallup Soul of the Community project was to measure citizens' engagement in each of the 26 KF communities in which they live. These reports add to the ongoing community narrative by showing how the citizens of the community feel about the place they live, what it has to offer them, and what they offer back to it. The data from this project are intended to be used to track the engagement of the community over time and to identify key strengths and opportunities for the communities. There is a statistical report for each community. 8 folders.
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community (continued), 2008 July (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Knight Center of Digital Excellence (KCoDE) and OneCommunity, 2007 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4903
      Executive summary and business plan for the Knight Center of Digital Excellence (CoDE). The mission of CoDE is to promote the use of broadband in support of community initiatives and to apply intellectual propoerty as well as hands-on expertise in helping communities to impact progress.
    - Knight Center of Digital Excellence (KCoDE) and OneCommunity, 2008 November (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
      Knight File Number - 4744
      Six volumes re: Intellectual Properties, Methodologies & Processes for the Knight Center of Digital Excellence (KCoDE). The mission of KCoDE is to promote the use of broadband in support of community initiatives and to apply intellectual property as well as hands-on expertise in helping communities to impact progress. (15 folders)
    - Knight Center of Digital Excellence (KCoDE) and OneCommunity (continued), 2008 November (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Knight Center of Digital Excellence (KCoDE) and OneCommunity (continued), 2008 November (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community, Narrative, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
      Knight File Number - 4984
      Updated version of July 2008 report. This report provides detailed quantitative data by community. A Life Expectations Index was added, along with an overall US benchmark that will allow comparisons of Knight Communities well being to national well being. The goal of the Knight Foundation-Gallup Soul of the Community project was to measure citizens' engagement in each of the 26 KF communities in which they live. These reports add to the ongoing community narrative by showing how the citizens of the community feel about the place they live, what it has to offer them, and what they offer back to it. The data from this project are intended to be used to track the engagement of the community over time and to identify key strengths and opportunities for the communities. There is a narrative report for each community. 3 folders.
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community (Overall, Aberdeen-Bradenton), 2009 July 16 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
      Knight File Number - 4985
      Revised version of the 2008 report, containing new information on Life Evaluation Index, Emotional Wellness and Media Engagement. The goal of the Knight Foundation-Gallup Soul of the Community project was to measure citizens' engagement in each of the 26 KF communities in which they live. These reports add to the ongoing community narrative by showing how the citizens of the community feel about the place they live, what it has to offer them, and what they offer back to it. The data from this project are intended to be used to track the engagement of the community over time and to identify key strengths and opportunities for the communities. There is a statistical report for each community and one for communities overall. 14 folders.
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community (Charlotte-Miami), 2009 July 16 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community (Milledgeville-Wichita), 2009 July 16 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - Gallup Report: Soul of the Community, 2009 January 23-December 17 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
      Knight File Number - 5257
      Memos, presentations, reports, news releases, etc. on the launch of the Soul of the Community 2009 study and planning for roll-out of 2010 data. Includes "Suggestions for Ramping Up the Soul of the Community Project" and "KF Community Strategy" by Loflin; preliminary results and a white paper by Gallup; and Board Presentation by Ellis and key messages for reporters. 2 folders
    - Knight Soul of the Community, 2010 October (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 5260
      Year three of the study. This report provides detailed quantitative data by community. The goal of the Knight Soul of the Community project was to measure citizens' engagement in each of the 26 KF communities in which they live. These reports add to the ongoing community narrative by showing how the citizens of the community feel about the place they live, what it has to offer them, and what they offer back to it. The data from this project are intended to be used to track the engagement of the community over time and to identify key strengths and opportunities for the communities. There is a narrative report for each community. 3 folders.
    - Gallup 2010 Timetable and Key Meetings (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4776
      Memos, reports, proposals, meeting materials, media training materials and reports re: planning and implementation for the launch of the third year results of the Gallup Soul of the Community report. Also includes suggestions on parlaying opportunities for enhanced grantmaking in the communities.
    - Knight Soul of the Community, 2010 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
      Knight File Number - 5259
      Powerpoint Presentations on the results of Year 3 of the Gallup research in the Soul of the Community. Includes several presentations tailored to specific KF communities. 2 folders.
    - Knight Soul of the Community (continued), 2010 October (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Knight Soul of the Community, 2011 February 15-November 30 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5261
      Memos, media report, presentation, letters, and meeting materials on continued efforts to disseminate information on the Knight Soul of the Community 2010 report. Includes information on the Bridgespan Group which was considered for some follow up work.
    - Knight Soul of the Community: Community Implications, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5262
      Report on KF communities highlighting what the Knight Soul of the Community 2010 report says about each community. Also includes Gallup Recommendations and Opportunities to Prioritize report.
    - Knight Soul of the Community, 2012 January-November 15 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5263
      Budget summaries, strategy document, meeting materials, memos, and presentations concerned with formulating a strategy for expanding understanding, and use of, the Knight Soul of the Community data. The Bridgespan Group assisted Knight in formulating the plan.
    - Bridgespan Group Materials, 2011-2012 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5264
      Recommendations and an implementation plan developed by The Bridgespan Group to disseminate, and use, data from the Knight Soul of the Community reports.
  - National Venture Fund, 2004-2013; 11; 0.95 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes and 1 half letter box
    - Early Childhood Funders' Collaborative, 2004-2006 August (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4972
      Background materials on the collaborative of funders concerned with the welfare of children from newly arrived families. Knight Foundation supported the collaborative. Also included is a Mid-Year Brief: Selected Highlights from a Cluster Evaluation of Knight Foundation Early Childhood Investments, August 2006.
    - Four Freedoms Fund, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4971
      Background materials, including budget, meeting materials, proposals, history, and newsclippings about the Four Freedoms Fund, which is concerned with safeguarding immigrant civil liberties and increasing partcipation among newcomers in civic and political life. KF was a major donor to the fund.
    - Community Partners in Arts Access, 2005 June-2007 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5487
      Three reports prepared by Mark Stern and Susan Seifert of the Social Impact of the Arts Project, University of Pennsylvania re: evaluations of the Community Partners in Arts Access initiative of KF for the Philadelphia and Camden, NJ communities.
    - CUREx Program Evaluation, 2006 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5488
      The evaluation was prepared by the Patrizi Associates and is titled, "Urban Fellows Gain Experience and Knowledge on Best Practices in Urban Redevelopment Through the CUREx Program" at the University of Pennsylvania.
    - Economic Impact of EITC Spending in Palm Beach County, Florida, c. 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5489
      The report is an analysis of the United Way of Palm Beach County's VITA Program which provided a range of services including free tax preparation. KF supported VITA centers in the most disadvantaged areas of Palm Beach County. The goal was to encourage all tax payers eligible for the EITC (Earned Income Tax Credit) to take it.
    - Coastal Carolina StepUp! Initiative Reports, 2006 September-2007 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5490
      Three reports prepared by Philliber Research Associates: Data from Faith-based Capacity Building Survey; Senior Staff Survey; and Evaluation Report of the Coastal Carolina StepUp! Initiative.
    - Knight New Media, 2007 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 5491
      This final evaluation report was prepared by Fetterman & Associates
    - Bendixen Survey, 2007 August 23-2008 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 4361
      Proposal by Bendixen & Associates to conduct research in each of the Knight communities in order to understand how opinion leaders and opinion makers in each of these cities view the Foundation and its impact on their community. Also included is a proposed agenda for a conference call with Bendixen associates; draft of an executive interview guide; Bendixen Survey report, "Knight Foundation: A Generous and Involved Giver, Widely Known: A leadership survey of the KF in its 26 communities"; summary of key points from 2007 survey results; Powerpoint presentation; TLC Committee Powerpoint presentation (this committee of KF employees was established in 2008 to recommend steps to improve the areas highlighted in the Bendixen survey) and an update by Paula Ellis on Customer Perception and Leadership Surveys.
    - CEP and Bendixen Results, 2007 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 4897
      Memo from Belinda Lawrence to the KF staff outlining the steps staff should follow in analyzing the data from the two surveys done of KF stakeholders.
    - Knight Foundation Investment in Education, 2008 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 4308
      Copy of a Powerpoint presentation by Paula Ellis to the Board of Trustees re: KF Investment in Education 1950-2007. Also included is an email from Eric Newton adding information on KF investment in journalism education.
    - Bendixen Survey Report and Lake Research Partners Report, 2009 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 4675
      "A Study of Community Leaders on the Impact of the Knight Foundation in 26 American Cities and Towns" is an update to the original 2007 study by Bendixen & Associates. This new study, "finds noteworthy progress in virtually all areas important to the foundation - along with room for additional improvement." Also included is a report by Lake Research Partners, "Knight Foundation: Quality Control Review of Knight Foundation Community Leaders Survey 2009". The report summarized findings from a quality control survey among a subset of respondents of the original Bendixen survey.
    - Bendixen Survey Appendix, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 5071
      Appendix to the report by Bendixen & Associates who produced a survey of KF's 26 communities. Includes executive interview guide, detailed cross-tabulations, and individual responses by Knight communities.
    - Ashoka Future Forum, 2010 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4746
      Memo from Paula Ellis to KF staff re: Ashoka Future Forum and the fellows induction ceremony, which took place April 6, 2010 at the Newseum in Washington, DC. The event was hosted by KF to commemorate its 30th year of Ashoka support. Also included is a map showing fellows in KF communities.
    - Atlantic Avenue Connected Corridor Project, 2011 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5303
      Final Evaluation Report prepared by Behavioral Assessment, Inc. The project was implemented by the Long Beach Community Foundation from October 2007 to February 2011 with funding from KF. The Corridor was selected because it bisects the city of Long Beach from north to south and is reflective of the diversity of the city.
    - National and Strategic Initiatives, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5250
      Powerpoint presentation on National Portfolio: Informed and Engaged Communities and list of team members' responsibilities.
    - Portfolio of Summer Projects, 2012 July 10 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5251
      Report on National grants prepared by intern Elliott McCarthy includes a flow chart of the Grant Goals Setting Process, grant write-ups, and a programmatic assessment.
    - Soul of the Community: Directory of Higher Education Community Engagement-Related Projects and People, 2010 April 5 (Box 2)
      Knight File Number - 4896
      Report from Katherine Loflin lists information on Organization, Project, Website, and Special Notes by KF community provides information on potential collaborators.
    - Immigration Initiative, 2005-2013; 1
      - Local Immigrant Integration Initiative for Miami-Dade/Broward, FL, c. 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4655
        Report includes sections on Key Aspects of the Foreign-Born Population in the U.S.; Key Aspects of the Foreign-Born Population in Miami-Dade/Broward; Statistics on Immigration in Knight Communities; Knight Community Comparisons; National Venture Fund's Immigration Integration Strategy; Q & A about the initiative; and the American Dream Fund.
      - Strengths and Needs: Young Children of Immigrants in 14 Knight Foundation Communities, 2007 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4739
        Report was prepared by the Migration Policy Institute, Washington, DC and uses analysis of US census data to provide a detailed overview of the socioeconomic conditions in which young children of immigrants lived in 2000, both in the nation as a whole and in the 14 US communities served by the KF American Dream Fund.
      - Immigration Reports, c. 2005-2011 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 5249
        Young Children of Immigrants in the Philadelphia Knight Community, c. 2005; Immigrant Integration Initiative report, c. 2005; American Dream Fund Program & Evaluation Update, December 2007; Civic Participation Fact Sheet, 2007; Engaging Immigrants, Organizations, and Coalitions - 2007 Comprehensive Summary Evaluation report, December 2007; Strengthening the Grassroots Movement, December 2007 and two reports prepared by Rob Paral and Associates: Key Information on Immigrant Civic Potential, and Profiles of Immigrant Communities Including Estimates of Legal Immigrants Eligible to Naturalize.
      - Immigration Initiative, 2007 September 7-2013 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5248
        Meeting agenda and participant lists, background information, proposed strategies, news release, statistics, grant reports, and charts used for development of a collaborative initiative to naturalize eligible immigrants.
      - Tempering the Immigration Debate: An Assessment of the American Dream Fund, 2008 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4307
        A reporter analysis by Tony Mecia. Mr. Mecia was hired by Knight Foundation to prepare an analysis on the effectiveness of the American Dream Fund, whose purpose was to fund a wide array of local, grassroots nonprofits in Knight communities. This report includes a document review and interview with nearly 20 people involved in all facets of the American Dream Fund.
  - Strategic Planning, 1991-2017; 12; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
    These files contain strategic planning materials for the Foundation in general (1991-1992), the Education Program (1995), and the Journalism Program (1995). Five folders relate to a "Planning Activities and Background: 1950-1990" report, including "Strategic PlanPhases I and II (1981-1982) with background on planning for the bequest from J.S. Knight, the John S. Knight Fellowship at Stanford, and planning for the future. There is also "Sharpen the Focus -- Heighten the Impact" plan (1992), which discusses priorities and plans for all four program areas, and has a ten-year financial plan. The "Strategic Planning Review" folder (1995) contains the goals, objectives and strategies for all programs, as well as additional material relating to planning for the Education Program. This review was facilitated by Nancy Raybin of Arthur Raybin and Associates. The "Journalism Program Update" folder holds the results of the strategic planning efforts for that program in 1992, and its progress to June 1995. Also included are a Knight Foundation Strategic Plan Goals and Objectives (1997); two copies of a Strategic Plan/Situational Analysis prepared by The Conservation Company in 2000; Community Relationships Task Force meeting materials (2000-2001) and a Strategic Planning Report, prepared by TCC and background readings (2005).
    - Planning Activities and Background, 1950-1990, 1991 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      Knight File Number - 1386